<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Darren Mothersele</title>
    <description>Creative Technologist, Drupal Training, Drupal Development, Drupal Consulting</description>
    <link>http://www.darrenmothersele.com</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.darrenmothersele.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>PHP Processing Pipeline</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#39;re faced with refactoring a huge bunch of sequential code
then a pipeline may be the answer.
With a processing pipeline you create your code in stages.
Then you compose the stages into a pipeline, and pass your
input for processing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is great because each of the stages can be easily tested
independently. It also makes the code much easier to read and
maintain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s a nice and simple implementation published by the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://thephpleague.com/&quot;&gt;League of Extraordinary Packages&lt;/a&gt;.
I&amp;#39;ve created a fork (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/darrenmothersele/pipeline&quot;&gt;on GitHub here&lt;/a&gt;)
which offers an even simpler syntax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#39;s a very basic example to show off this new syntax.
You create your stages as simple classes with an invoke method.
For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-php&quot; data-lang=&quot;php&quot;&gt;class Double {
    public function __invoke($payload)
    {
        return $payload * 2;
    }
}

class Square {
    public function __invoke($payload)
    {
        return $payload * $payload;
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could even pass in parameters to the stage constructor:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-php&quot; data-lang=&quot;php&quot;&gt;class Add {
    private $i;
    public function __construct($i)
    {
        $this-&amp;gt;i = $i;
    }
    public function __invoke($payload)
    {
        return $payload + $this-&amp;gt;i;
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then create a &lt;code&gt;Pipeline&lt;/code&gt; to chain the stages together:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-php&quot; data-lang=&quot;php&quot;&gt;$pipe = (new Pipeline-&amp;gt;Double()-&amp;gt;Square()-&amp;gt;Add(10);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then you can process values using the Pipeline:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-php&quot; data-lang=&quot;php&quot;&gt;echo $pipe-&amp;gt;process(10), PHP_EOL;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can even process a list of values:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-php&quot; data-lang=&quot;php&quot;&gt;var_dump(array_map($pipe, [1, 2, 3]));
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously you are not just limited to processing integers as in these
examples. XML documents, converting to JSON, filtering, translating
and other transformations are great candidates for pipelines stages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve submitted a pull request for my simple modification. All I did
was add an implementation of the &lt;code&gt;__invoke()&lt;/code&gt; method so you can
add stages without having to explicitly &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt;-up objects and
pass them into the &lt;code&gt;pipe()&lt;/code&gt; method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully my pull request gets accepted. The only thing to be aware
of is that I made use of the variadic operator, so it needs a PHP
version of 5.6 or greater.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.darrenmothersele.com//blog/2016/02/11/processing-pipelines-php/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.darrenmothersele.com//blog/2016/02/11/processing-pipelines-php/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Future of (My) Web Part 3 - Rethinking Twitter</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I feel sorry for Twitter. It&amp;#39;s never been sure what it&amp;#39;s supposed to be. Twitter pioneered and popularised the idea of microblogging, then  almost killed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of my ongoing experiment I have stopped using
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.darrenmothersele.com/blog/2015/12/03/work-in-progress/&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.darrenmothersele.com/blog/2016/01/27/why-i-left-whatsapp/&quot;&gt;WhatsApp&lt;/a&gt;. The decision is not as simple this time as I don&amp;#39;t want to completely remove myself from Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What&amp;#39;s wrong with Twitter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I joined Twitter in April 2008 while at the first Social Innovation camp. The camp organisers used Twitter to broadcast messages to all attendees. It was useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twitter&amp;#39;s functionality was simple. It became a great example of how innovation can come from users. Features such as hash-tags emerged from how people used the technology. Compare this with other services that learnt how to limit and control their users by progressively introducing features. Such as Facebook&amp;#39;s slow boiling of the privacy frog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twitter is another corporate controlled silo. And, compared to the lo-fi, elegant, and clean idea of 140 character public messaging, Twitter today is a mess. My stream flooded with image spam posted to draw attention to tweets. And, unnecessary screenshots of text posted to bypass the limited message size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;How I Currently use Twitter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To plan my future relationship with Twitter I have first looked at
how I currently use the service. I&amp;#39;ve identified the following types of usage:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;0. Aggregator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a network of friends and colleagues in digital technology, creative coding, free software, and other interests. Twitter collects the thoughts, opinions, and silliness from this eclectic mix of people. This makes it fun and serious, informative and weird.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wouldn&amp;#39;t find this variety of updates if they were not all aggregated into once place. But, at the same time, this can be a distracting waste of time. And it&amp;#39;s getting harder to filter out the signal from the noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;1. Live-blogging&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I&amp;#39;m at an event with Wifi signal I tend to tweet a lot more than usual. I &lt;em&gt;live-blog&lt;/em&gt; my experience of the event, mainly for my own benefit. This makes it easier to remember what I did when I review the event afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;2. RSS feed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in the day, people would subscribe to my RSS feed to get updated when I added new content to my site. Since Google killed RSS when they shut down Reader, nobody seems to do that anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use Twitter to post up bits from my own blog and writing, with links back to my site. Using it as a way to let people know I&amp;#39;ve posted something new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;3. Web Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also post up quotes and links to things I&amp;#39;ve found on the net. Useful stuff I&amp;#39;ve found for work, quotes for inspiration, or things related to my interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;4. Observations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I feel the need to comment on things I observe. I particularly enjoy paradox and inconsistency. If I have my phone on me, and I&amp;#39;m in the right mood, I share on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;5. Conversation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twitter is a noisy place to try and have a conversation with people. I love how anyone can chime in and join a conversation. I always enjoy hearing from other points of view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I start public conversations with companies that have disappointed me. It&amp;#39;s a way to get a response, when they don&amp;#39;t answer the phone or emails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;6. Brain-dump&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I just post up random thoughts I&amp;#39;ve been having. Maybe these are things I don&amp;#39;t need to shout out to the world. But stuff I still want to log somewhere. Twitter isn&amp;#39;t the correct place for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Alternative to Twitter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still want to engage with my network on Twitter. But I want to decouple my communication from the silo. This is what the Indie Web refer to as &lt;a href=&quot;https://indiewebcamp.com/POSSE&quot;&gt;POSSE&lt;/a&gt; (Post on Own Site, Syndicate Elsewhere).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve been thinking of what I&amp;#39;d like to build as an alternative to Twitter.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.darrenmothersele.com/blog/2015/07/12/happy-birthday-bucky/&quot;&gt;Buckminster Fuller&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#39;s Dymaxion Chronofile comes to mind. Bucky documented his entire life, from the point where he started to live his life as an experiment, in what he called a &amp;quot;Chronofile&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have already implemented a private &amp;quot;idea log&amp;quot;. This is somewhere to post all the random thoughts that are not yet fully formed. This helps me collect disparate thoughts and allow them to coalesce
into something more considered. It creates space in my mind by getting things out of my head. Working like a real extension to my memory, some things stick around. But, also like real memory, I need a way to forget. Sometimes, it&amp;#39;s good to let go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Posting notes to my own site, and syndicating them to Twitter, is now top of my list. This will be the next feature to develop for my website.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.darrenmothersele.com//blog/2016/02/02/rethinking-twitter/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.darrenmothersele.com//blog/2016/02/02/rethinking-twitter/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>My First Front-end London</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Last night I got to attend &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.frontendlondon.co.uk/&quot;&gt;FEL&lt;/a&gt; for the first time. The popular meetup, hosted by &lt;a href=&quot;http://madebymany.com/&quot;&gt;Made by Many&lt;/a&gt;, celebrating it&amp;#39;s 3rd anniversary last night. I have
&lt;a href=&quot;https://calumryan.com/&quot;&gt;Calum Ryan&lt;/a&gt;, fellow Indiewebber, to thank for sorting me out a ticket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calum was up first talking about &lt;a href=&quot;http://indiewebcamp.com/&quot;&gt;#indieweb&lt;/a&gt;. He summarised the movement well. The talk gave detail of the motivations, principles, and technology. I was happy to learn that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/TR/2016/WD-webmention-20160112/&quot;&gt;Webmention has a first draft of a W3C standard&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was encouraging to hear this was Calum&amp;#39;s first presentation. A great start, and I hope he continues on this path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then &lt;a href=&quot;http://bodil.lol/&quot;&gt;Bodil Stokke&lt;/a&gt; took us on a tour of generators in ES6. This makes me want to do more Javascript. If only because I have a thing for the world &lt;em&gt;yield&lt;/em&gt;. It might be my favourite word. I love all that it implies. For me, in conjures up images of Taoism, effortless action, and the path of least resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of particular interest was the backwards use of generators as consumers used in monads. We saw generators combined with Promises to write asynchronous code without callbacks. Simply beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The presentation is &lt;a href=&quot;http://bodil.lol/generators/&quot;&gt;online here&lt;/a&gt;.
I also made a note to check out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com/tj/co&quot;&gt;Co library&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrapping up the trio of speakers for the night was &lt;a href=&quot;http://macr.ae/&quot;&gt;Callum Macrae&lt;/a&gt;.
With more Ls and more LOLs that the first Calum.
He took us on a humorous tour of ES6, under the guise of deprecating jQuery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We saw how to replace jQuery features with native Javascript. With a polyfil, or transpiling, it seems jQuery does not add anything. Native Javascript winning on features in some cases. Callum also added that the overhead of using Babel is less than including jQuery. So there is no need for jQuery. Unless you want &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/rwaldron/8720084#file-reasons-md&quot;&gt;old browser compatibility&lt;/a&gt; or are using a library with a dependency on jQuery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An entertaining and informative night. I&amp;#39;ll definitely be back.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.darrenmothersele.com//blog/2016/01/29/my-first-frontend-london/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.darrenmothersele.com//blog/2016/01/29/my-first-frontend-london/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Drupal Predictions for 2016</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This will be a momentus year for Drupal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David H, Drupal.org webmaster, was
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/FromWayDowntown/status/692375858175148032&quot;&gt;soliciting responses&lt;/a&gt;
to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.drupal.org/node/2652402&quot;&gt;this thread&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter.
I kept my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.drupal.org/node/2652402#comment-10792382&quot;&gt;predictions&lt;/a&gt;
brief, but thought I would post here to elaborate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people may be predicting &lt;a href=&quot;https://securityintelligence.com/news/new-year-new-problems-cms-vulnerabilites-take-on-2016/&quot;&gt;a year of security vulnerabilities&lt;/a&gt;. I believe we have a
year of innovation ahead of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drupal&amp;#39;s ecosystem of contributed modules is playing catch-up since the
release of version 8. It has been years since CCK and Views were just
experiments in the contrib module space.
They are now established as foundation of Drupal core.
Contrib (the wider community of Drupal developers) can now get back to innovating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Get back to innovating&amp;quot; isn&amp;#39;t much of a prediction. I thought about it
some more and came up with three things I think are likely to happen in 2016...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;CMS-as-a-Service&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The era of the monolythic, does-it-all, CMS is coming to an end.
The Drupal community talk a lot about &lt;em&gt;progressive decoupling&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://buytaert.net/should-we-decouple-drupal-with-a-client-side-framework&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://buytaert.net/selecting-a-client-side-framework-for-drupal&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;.
But, the idea of a &lt;em&gt;fully decoupled&lt;/em&gt; backend is becoming established
in other areas. Services like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.contentful.com/&quot;&gt;Contentful&lt;/a&gt; already
provide a fully decoupled, headless CMS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Systems become decoupled, we move to a microservice architecture, and evaluate server-less options. It is conceivable that a Content API could become part of the infrastructure. Amazon are the leading Infrastructure-as-a-Service provider. A Content API (or CMS-as-a-Service) would fit in their suite of cloud computing services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did an experiment recently where I put Amazon&amp;#39;s API Gateway in front of an EC2 instance running Drupal. This gives a more robust API on top of Drupal 8&amp;#39;s Rest support. Monitoring, traffic management, and flexible security controls are standard.
This approach offers several advantages, including: &lt;a href=&quot;http://swagger.io/&quot;&gt;Swagger&lt;/a&gt; support;
CloudFront caching for performance; and input/output
translation with data models defined with JSON schema.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Acquia IPO&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going public was always on the cards for Acquia, but they said they
&lt;a href=&quot;http://bostinno.streetwise.co/2015/10/21/acquia-engage-ceo-talks-content-hub-valuation-ipo/&quot;&gt;are in no rush to IPO&lt;/a&gt;. This could be the year. Adoption of D8 will being changes
to the user base and continued adoption at the enterprise level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be accompanied by more consolidation in the Drupal world.
One of the biggest risks I see is with Drupal companies taking on
bigger projects. A single client becomes a large contributer to their
revenue, in some cases I&amp;#39;ve heard as much as 70%. This is a risky situation
to be in, if you rely on one client for a majority of your business.
The solution is for Drupal companies to come together to form larger entities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is just a continuation of an existing trend.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wunderkraut.com/blog/worlds-largest-drupal-provider-created-by-merger/2012-08-20&quot;&gt;Wunderkraut&lt;/a&gt;,
was the most high-profile merger in the community.
Followed by many more, involving companies such as
&lt;a href=&quot;http://wearepropeople.com/news/propeople-and-blink-reaction-come-together-to-form-ffw-a-new-global-digital-agency&quot;&gt;FFW&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mediacurrent.com/blog/mediacurrent-acquired-by-code-and-theory&quot;&gt;MediaCurrent&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.phase2technology.com/blog/phase2-and-opensourcery-whats-new-in-portland/&quot;&gt;Phase2&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href=&quot;http://i-kos.com/press-release/2014-09-22/mogdesign-joins-ikos-digital-accelerate-drupal-growth&quot;&gt;i-Kos&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Composer Support and Decoupled Components&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Composer support in Drupal needs some work.
There are some big wins to be had by embracing the
Composer (and Packagist) workflow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commerce Guys are leading the way with Drupal Commerce. They have been
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/commerceguys&quot;&gt;factoring out components into separate libraries&lt;/a&gt;.
Other PHP projects beyond Drupal are making use of them, and contributing to
their development.
Expect more contrib projects to factor out separate PHP packages of re-usable code.
Then Drupal modules become just a thin layer of glue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been a trend for PHP Frameworks to decouple their core components.
The Symfony Components split from the full stack framework has
meant much wider adoption. They are used in &lt;a href=&quot;http://symfony.com/projects&quot;&gt;many PHP projects&lt;/a&gt;,
including Drupal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PHP-FIG exists to promote interoperability between frameworks. This year will see further initiatives to clean up Drupal&amp;#39;s code. Such as, removal of anti-patterns like service locator. The eventual aim will be to decoupling components from Drupal core.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can you imagine using Views on a non-drupal project?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2016 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.darrenmothersele.com//blog/2016/01/28/drupal-predictions/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.darrenmothersele.com//blog/2016/01/28/drupal-predictions/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Work in Progress: The Future of (My) Web (Part 2, Leaving WhatsApp)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve deleted WhatsApp. I wasn&amp;#39;t going to post about this,
as I don&amp;#39;t want to sound like a broken record.
But, as several people have emailed me asking why,
I thought I would explain my decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.darrenmothersele.com/blog/2015/12/03/work-in-progress/&quot;&gt;posted about this before&lt;/a&gt;
when I left Facebook.
I&amp;#39;m not just ranting about data surveillance and privacy concerns.
I have other concerns about our relationship with technology. There are
certain ideas that are in danger of becoming locked in unless
we come up with alternatives.
My attitude is solution focused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So WhatsWrong with WhatsApp?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;It&amp;#39;s free.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They annouced recently that they are removing the subscription and making the service free.
There is now no doubt what the real business model is.
You are not their customer, you are their product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;No API&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brian Acton, WhatsApp cofounder, has publicly stated that there will never be an API.
Interoperability is never going to be an option with Whatsapp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compare with email: You use gmail, someone else uses hotmail, and I have my own email
software I built myself. We can all freely email each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;re on different mobile networks, but we can still freely send each other SMS messages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will never be the case with WhatsApp.
If you&amp;#39;re not on WhatsApp you don&amp;#39;t exist.
WhatsApp is a monoculture silo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to be part of building an independent, open future.
The involves removing myself from networks that don&amp;#39;t support open standards, interoperability, and diversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the principle of &amp;quot;selfdogfooding&amp;quot;, removing myself gives me the motiviation
I need to build and contribute to an alternative
&lt;a href=&quot;http://indiewebcamp.com/&quot;&gt;Indie Web&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;The IndieWeb is a people-focused alternative to the ‘corporate web’.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.darrenmothersele.com//blog/2016/01/27/why-i-left-whatsapp/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.darrenmothersele.com//blog/2016/01/27/why-i-left-whatsapp/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Buckminster Fuller, in Plain English</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.darrenmothersele.com/blog/2015/07/12/happy-birthday-bucky/&quot;&gt;wrote a blog post&lt;/a&gt;
to commemorate Buckminster Fuller&amp;#39;s birthday back in July,
and have now returned to his works. I am watching again
his lecture series &amp;quot;Everything I Know&amp;quot;.
There are many important messages and deep lessons in Bucky&amp;#39;s lectures that
still apply today. I am only
starting to scratch the surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I watch, and follow the transcripts, I am
working on my own set of notes.
I hope by rewriting Bucky&amp;#39;s words in plain english
I can help make these lessons accessible to more people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/buckminsterfuller&quot;&gt;video series uploaded to archive.org&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&quot;https://bfi.org/about-fuller/resources/everything-i-know/session-1&quot;&gt;transcribed here&lt;/a&gt;
as the source of these works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Everything I Know by Buckminster Fuller&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An attempt to better understand the lessons of Buckminster Fuller, by translating into Plain English.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Session 1 - Part 1&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are all born naked, helpless, and ignorant. That’s where humanity has always started. We have had to find our own way, by trial and error, driven by instinctive urges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans have been on our planet for millions of years with very little physiological change. In India and China, as far back as 5,000 years ago, we were thinking extraordinarily well about our experience and the principles of our universe. Astonishing, in view of the limited amount of information humanity had at that time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, because we have systems to record information, we can see the rapid rate at which it is increasing. We can’t keep track of the rate at which we are discovering more. Like a child, formed in the womb for nine months, being born into an entire new world — we are coming out of a common womb of ignorance, transitioning into a new relationship with the universe. Not, as a divided humanity spread across the planet, but as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are living as people of the world. Things thought impossible become reality within a generation. Things once dismissed as nonsense, become typical. None of it was planned. There was nobody in previous generations prophesying about the impossibles that are happening today. Not one of these steps was anticipated by any of the preceding. But, no sooner than it has happened, the human says “I knew it all the time. I’m not one of those who are suprised… I was a little bit responsible.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a strange vanity inherent in humans. Essential to being born naked and helpless, and having to make the fantastic number of mistakes in order to learn. Without which, we would have become disgruntled, and dismayed by our mistakes, and not been able to carry on. And so we were given this strange vanity so we are able to decieve ourselves. Like saying “getting to the moon, anybody can do that. It’s simple and logical.” Now it’s obvious, but only because it happened in your lifetime, and you can see how it happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Session 1 - Part 2&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When people say natural they mean as it was in their day. As rules and customs change over time, so the young people begin to see things differently. Any tension between generations is down to the young being born into a new natural, which is unnatural to their elders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lily might assume it was always going to be a seed, then it grows up and gets leaves, then it flowers. Each of these changes a surprise. Patterns like this operate on humanity too, but the vanity of human beings is such that they don’t like to be caught by surprise. Humans have always had troubles, but have never before been so aware of the troubles of others, and so aware of the totality of great trouble. The vanity factor again makes them feel responsible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If something is unfamiliar we say it is artificial or unnatural. There is nothing artifical or unnatural. If nature permits it, it is natural. If nature doesn’t permit it, you can’t do it. You may not be familiar with the fact nature allows it, but your unfamiliarity doesn’t make it unnatural.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our earth is 8,000 miles diameter, a hundredth the size of the sun, our star, which itself is a minor star. From the moon you can’t make out a mountain on earth, let alone a human being. The aberration of the highest mountain to the deepest depth of the ocean, when taken over 8,000 miles of the earth’s diameter, is insignificant. A polished steel ball is rougher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are invisible on a tiny planet. Orbiting a negligible little star. Which is one of a hundred billion stars in one of a known billion galaxies. As tiny as we are, we have information of an 11 1/2 light year radius. The fact that we have this kind of capability, despite our physical insignificance, hints that we have some very great significance in the scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t know of any other phenomena that has this mind. There are many creatures that have brains, each combine individual senses to create a special case. But the human mind we find able to do something that the brain cannot do. To review the special case experiences, and from time to time intuit that something else is going on. Something that was not predicted or suggested by the special case experiences considered only by themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The earliest annals of man record five bright lights in the sky. Much smaller than the sun and the moon, but behaving in ways the other myriad of lights in the sky did not. The others stayed constant, but these five moved around and were a little brighter than the others. We tracked where they would appear and saw regularities. Good recordings of these behaviours were made, of what we began to call the planets. Five special cases differentiated by their unique behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;TBC...&lt;/h3&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2016 02:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.darrenmothersele.com//blog/2016/01/26/buckminster-fuller-in-plain-english/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.darrenmothersele.com//blog/2016/01/26/buckminster-fuller-in-plain-english/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The clouds made me do it...</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Dear Algorithm,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have no idea what I’m doing. But you do. Notwithstanding statistical anomalies and a slight margin of error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at the clouds in the sky. You might recognise the stratus and cumulus. But, you can’t see the timid blue with brave orange flourishes that I experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This unique display, never before seen, and never to appear again, can never be predicted in all its beautiful complexity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simple to observe and experience. Impossible to know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your models can guess what I will do. But I am one with the clouds, and you will never know me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Love,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Human&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2016 01:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.darrenmothersele.com//blog/2016/01/26/the-clouds-made-me-do-it/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.darrenmothersele.com//blog/2016/01/26/the-clouds-made-me-do-it/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Session submission guidelines for conferences and camps</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week I found out that the date for my nephew&amp;#39;s christening has changed. This means I can now make it to the Drupal Camp in London. I decided to propose a session so that I can share my recent insights, research, and learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Drupal Camp London team have kept the session submission process minimal. This makes it easy for people to submit proposals, but it makes it unclear what the expectations are. What are they looking for in proposed sessions? How long are the sessions expected to be? What is the review process?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I only found out I could attend at the last minute, I had no time to enquire about the process. So I made some assumptions based on my experiences of programming at previous camps. I also did some research into other Drupal camp and conference session submission processes.
The &lt;a href=&quot;https://amsterdam2014.drupal.org/news/session-selection-drupalcon-inside-out.html&quot;&gt;Amsterdam Drupalcon site&lt;/a&gt; had this to say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;There’s a lot of elements to session selection. We need to make sure that sessions are of value to a wide audience. The presenters must be engaging speakers who can interest a large crowd of attendees. We try as hard as we can to bring in new (to DrupalCon) speakers, and speakers who bring something from outside of the Drupal sphere. We want to make sure that the diversity of the community is represented and encouraged. And we need to work across track teams to ensure that one speaker is not speaking in several tracks; both for the sake of their stress and sanity in preparing the talks and to ensure that everyone who applied has the best chance of speaking. Finally, we need to make sure that sessions fit both the theme of the track and of the conference.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the &lt;a href=&quot;https://events.drupal.org/barcelona2015/session-submission-live&quot;&gt;Barcelona Drupalcon&lt;/a&gt; offered the following 3 part session submission formula...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part 1: Describe a compelling topic that affects the reader directly, maybe a pain point, or juicy new technology. &lt;br&gt;
Part 2: Allude to your solution, sharing just enough that the reader has a moment of &amp;quot;I need that ...how do I not know this already?&amp;quot; &lt;br&gt;
Part 3: Explain how awesome the session will be because you are going to cover &amp;quot;XYZ&amp;quot; and make the reader&amp;#39;s life so much better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;My session selection criteria&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realised that I&amp;#39;ve done session selection myself many times. At every conference, camp, and symposium I attend I make my own selection of sessions to attend. The key to making the most out of attending a conference is to attend the right sessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Resonate last year I set the intention of broadening my horizons, so intentionally selected session that I would not normally be exposed to. And sessions that offered something new. At DrupalCon in Amsterdam I set the intension of getting as deep into Drupal 8 as possible. So I attended every D8 session I could. Selecting the sessions I thought offered the most opportunity for learning. It helps if they are recognisable names, or people I&amp;#39;ve seen present before and know they do a good session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I think about my own criteria, I get it down to five things...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Importance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this definitely a session worth attending? Is the session topic cutting edge, or immediately relevant to my situation. Is it ground breaking or offer a significant contribution to the field?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Purpose&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this the right type of session? Is the purpose of the session clear? Does the description make it clear what the expected participant outcomes are? Does the description give enough specific information to make me want to know more?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Motivation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is the session motivated by theory, practice, and/or research? Is this presented in a detailed, thorough, and comprehensible way?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Substantiated&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are all claims (practices, conclusions, proposals) well substantiated. Is the speaker presenting something they know about? Is the speaker well positioned to be giving the session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Clarity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is the session proposal clear? A well written session description indicates the presentation itself will be of professional quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope I managed to purvey these five points in my own
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.darrenmothersele.com/blog/2016/01/21/survive-and-thrive-drupal-8/&quot;&gt;session proposal&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;#39;d love to hear from you if you have your own ideas about what makes a good Drupalcamp session. If you drop me a line or leave a comment I will take them into account while planning my own session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Darren&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.darrenmothersele.com//blog/2016/01/22/conference-session-submission-guidelines/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.darrenmothersele.com//blog/2016/01/22/conference-session-submission-guidelines/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Surviving - and thriving - during the transition to Drupal&amp;nbsp;8</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is my proposal for a session at the upcoming &lt;a href=&quot;http://drupalcamp.london/&quot;&gt;Drupal Camp in London&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drupal is going through some big changes. And, so is the world. Now may be an unsettled period, but, times of disturbance can also be times of great opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will share my experiences with Drupal and my research into how the web and society are transforming. This will include my personal manifesto and ideas about Drupal&amp;#39;s role in the future of the web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Drupal community helped me transform in many ways. I have had the opportunity to work on some of the biggest, flagship Drupal websites, and in teams of all sizes. I&amp;#39;ve grown and advanced as a developer and a human.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have also been difficult times. These have included my own personal challenges, and stories I have heard from others. In my work at &lt;a href=&quot;http://ideationnetworks.com/&quot;&gt;Ideation Networks&lt;/a&gt; I sit with clients as they weigh up the pros and cons of Drupal. Many organisations feel they have been burnt by Drupal. And, for some, PHP (and by association Drupal) is just not cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, on the whole, these are exciting times for Drupal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drupal 8 is the biggest achievement of our community to date. The latest version has been completely rewritten to use modern object-oriented PHP. We refer to this process as &amp;quot;getting off the island&amp;quot;. It means dropping the &amp;quot;not invented here&amp;quot; philosophy, and embracing the wider PHP community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drupal as a product, a community, and a movement, is our co-creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have all played a part in Drupal&amp;#39;s success: Dries and the core development team; the wider community of contributors; the attendees of Drupal camps and conferences; people who talk about Drupal; and the developers, agencies, companies and users that drive Drupal&amp;#39;s adoption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this session I will attempt to answer these questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What have we gained, and what have we sacrificed along the way?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NGOs, charities, smaller organisations, and hobbyists made up Drupal&amp;#39;s traditional user-base. Have we shunned them as we&amp;#39;ve chased the enterprise client and big budget projects? Or, does Drupal 8 bring more of these users back into the fold?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Now that we&amp;#39;ve got this amazing platform, what do we do with it?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Egyptian Revolution of 2011 is just one example of the web enabling real change in the world. How does Drupal fit into the bigger picture? How can we empower more positive change in the world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Where do we go next? How can Drupal continue to transform and grow?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone is talking about front-end frameworks, progressive decoupling, big pipe, micro-services. Innovation is more than just jumping on bandwagons. Considered from a deeper place, what do these trends tell us about the real changes that are happening? How does Drupal embrace these changes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m excited. There are some tensions to resolve, and some challenges ahead, but also big opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Join me for this session. Let&amp;#39;s explore transformation of our world, the web, Drupal, and ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.darrenmothersele.com//blog/2016/01/21/survive-and-thrive-drupal-8/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.darrenmothersele.com//blog/2016/01/21/survive-and-thrive-drupal-8/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>TinyLetter #2 - The Difficult Second Letter</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Backfill on 30/01/2016: Posting up my second TinyLetter for posterity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy new year! and welcome to my second TinyLetter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you missed &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.darrenmothersele.com/blog/2015/12/12/my-first-tinyletter/&quot;&gt;the first one&lt;/a&gt;, you are receiving this because you are on my list of friends and family. I don&amp;#39;t use Facebook, so this is a way to follow my updates. If you don&amp;#39;t want this, let me know or unsubscribe. No hard feelings! :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you to everyone who gave me feedback after &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/blog/2015/12/12/my-first-tinyletter/&quot;&gt;my first letter&lt;/a&gt;. It has been really great to hear people&amp;#39;s encouragement, and hear that other people are also starting to question the way we connect online, our relationship with technology, and the way technology is shaping us. Also, a big thank you to people who still invite me to things, despite not being on Facebook! :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone sent me &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/music/2015/dec/13/ed-sheeran-quits-social-media-instagram-world-tour&quot;&gt;an article from the Guardian&lt;/a&gt; about Ed Sheeran (pop star?) leaving social media for a year. He&amp;#39;s quoted as saying “I find myself seeing the world through a screen and not my eyes.” Perhaps Ed Sheeran will now go on a killing spree, thus proving the daily mail were correct when &lt;a href=&quot;http://http//www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2184658/Is-joining-Facebook-sign-youre-psychopath-Some-employers-psychologists-say-suspicious.html&quot;&gt;they reported&lt;/a&gt; that people not on social media are &amp;quot;abnormal,&amp;quot; &amp;quot;suspicious,&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;possibly even psychopaths&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you had a relaxing and restorative break, and had a great start to the year. Sometimes we&amp;#39;re forced to stop and relax. That&amp;#39;s what happened to me on new years eve, when I came down with a 24hr bug. Notwithstanding the bouts of vomiting, and missing Rob and Verity&amp;#39;s NYE party, it was a great start to the year. Resting, watching the fireworks out of the window from bed, and being entertained by the amazing Nikki!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New year is a time of reflection and resolution. For me, this year, resolutions don&amp;#39;t mean starting something or giving something up, but instead mean being resolute (purposeful) about continuing to simplify and live freely. This has been a gradual shift for me, but became a thing when Nikki and I named it. Several months ago, when we were out walking and talking, we coined the term &lt;em&gt;simplivfree&lt;/em&gt; - a portmanteau of the words &lt;em&gt;simply&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;living&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;free&lt;/em&gt;. It&amp;#39;s our joint manifesto for how we intend to live our life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember when we first came up with this phrase. We&amp;#39;d spent a day walking, with no real plan or aim. Something Nikki and I have taken to doing quite often. The great thing about being spontaneous is that it&amp;#39;s always a surprise where you end up. This particular day we ended up walking for several hours, along the canal, from west London, Ladbroke Grove, through Little Venice, by Regents Park, and eventually out at Camden and up to Primrose Hill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s magic that happens by the canal. The hustle and bustle of london fades away as soon as you go down to the tow path. It&amp;#39;s peaceful. No one is going anywhere fast. Apart from maybe the occasional cyclists or jogger, but they smile and say hi as they pass by. A slow walk among the communities of people living on boats demonstrates that there are many, very different, ways to live life. And that we have choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simplivfree has become our manifesto, our mantra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simply&lt;/strong&gt; = focusing on what&amp;#39;s important. It means finding the signal and filtering out the noise. Simple doesn&amp;#39;t necessarily mean easy, but if something seems hard or feels forced, then it&amp;#39;s probably not &amp;quot;the way&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Living&lt;/strong&gt; = being in the present moment. Getting real. Experiencing and making the most of every moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Free&lt;/strong&gt; = being independent. It means not being locked in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of replies to my previous letter commented that they couldn&amp;#39;t leave Facebook because they were locked in. For me, it&amp;#39;s a sacrifice I&amp;#39;m willing to make because I believe the potential gains of living more real are unbounded. Plus, it gives me the incentive I need to build my own tools, and contribute to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://indiewebcamp.com/&quot;&gt;IndieWeb&lt;/a&gt; (a people-focused alternative to the &amp;quot;corporate web&amp;quot;). This also plays out in my work, as I continue to attract clients that want to switch to open-source content management systems, rather than be locked into proprietary systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year I plan to go &amp;quot;serverless&amp;quot;. For readers who can relate to this, you will understand how much simpler my life will be when I don&amp;#39;t have several servers to manage. The challenge will be to do this, and retain independence. I&amp;#39;ll save the details of why this is a challenge, and how I think it can be solved, for a more technical post on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.darrenmothersele.com/blog/&quot;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorry, this letter has ended up much longer than I planned. But, I&amp;#39;ve saved the best news &amp;#39;til last...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Vows&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nikki and I are getting married! :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first joint &amp;quot;Simplivfree&amp;quot; project is to work out what that means to us. This will then guide us as we work out how best to celebrate our union. To do this, we&amp;#39;re embarking on a journey of learning about marriage in it&amp;#39;s many forms. We&amp;#39;re starting this as an open-source project (working title = The Vows) where we will compile everything we learn about engagements, weddings and marriages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to consider a wide variety of different approaches to marriage in our research, so we&amp;#39;re interested in talking to anyone who believes they could offer any insight - conventional or otherwise. How does marriage work in different cultures, inter-faith marriages, non-conventional relationships, weddings, and marriages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you know anyone who might be interested in having a conversation with us about this, please get in touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have a great month!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.darrenmothersele.com//blog/2016/01/17/second-tinyletter/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.darrenmothersele.com//blog/2016/01/17/second-tinyletter/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
